<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A true report of the late horrible murther committed by VVilliam Sherwood prisoner in the Queenes Benche, for the profession of Popery, the 18. of Iune. 1581.]</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12126</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22432</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103014</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838773</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838773</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3161</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12126)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3161)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1156:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A true report of the late horrible murther committed by VVilliam Sherwood prisoner in the Queenes Benche, for the profession of Popery, the 18. of Iune. 1581.]</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By John Charlewood and Edvvard VVhite,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1581]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from caption title; imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; as filmed title page too dark to read.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sherwood, William, d. 1581 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hobson, Richard, d. 1581 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Murder --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:3161:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3161:1"/>
            <head>¶ A true report of the late <hi>horrible murther committed</hi> by <hi>VVilliam Sherwood,</hi> Priſoner <hi>in the Queenes Benche, for the</hi> profeſſion of Popery, the 18. of <hi>Iune,</hi> 1581.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am the more loath at this</hi> time, to laie open vnto the view of the whole worlde, that late foule murder com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by <hi>Sherwood,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would not ſpeake much of them which be gonne, &amp; be thought to bite them by the back which are dead, and ſo be like vnto thoſe Papiſts which béeing hotte in cruelty, did not onely curſe the dead conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, but did take vp and burne the hones of diuers good men into aſhes, to ſignifie vnto the worlde, that no drinke could coole their thirſt, but blood, no Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice could content the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but the warme hart blood of Martyrs, &amp; the death of the Saints of God. But my intent is this, for as much as their ſcabbes now breake out, and that their cruelty ſéeketh no corners, but ſetteth it ſelfe vpon a Stage to be beheld of all men, to giue all good Chriſtians warning,
<pb facs="tcp:3161:2"/>that as they ſhall heare of theyr naughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and ſée it ſo, they will learne to ſpew them out of their ſtomackes for euer. It was wunt to be ſayd often, and to be true: Enuie braggeth, but draweth no blood. But nowe it may be as truelie ſayd: the mallice of a Papiſte, it braggeth lyttle, but it is hardſie ſatiffied, but with aboundaunce of much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>od.</p>
            <p>Theyr deſired time of reuenge is not paſt, and theyr mallice hath not yet vomit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his gall. We may ſée this, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe oportunitie offereth not it ſelfe, to let them delight their eies with beholding our channelles, running and reking, with the warme blood of Proteſtauntes: rather then they will want this delight, they will waſhe their handes in the blood of their owne brethren, in their owne chambers. This is the portion of their cupps, which if they might, we ſhould be made to drinke to the dregges.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Bores which deſtroy the Vineyard, who becauſe they are not baigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Dogs, and their eares torne off, they will play lyke madde Dogges them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, byting all that come in their way.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3161:2"/>
            <p>They giue out in their Lybelles which they ſcatter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ndlie advertiſements, as <hi>Indas</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aindlie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſſe. They caſt them ſelues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke and Subiectes, at the ſéete of our gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>me, but their long eares d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>wray their conditions. Their throates are open Sepulchres, they flatter with their tongues: and ſo is it their kinde, for it is as naturall for a Dogge to barke, as to wagge hé<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tayle: If the common wealth be not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of this infection, the plague will be ſo great, that vppon euerie good Proteſtauntes d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ord haue mercie vpon vs,</hi> may ſhortlis be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ritten.</p>
            <p>But I will bréefly deliuer out this fearfull Tragedy, in the which I will ſet out nothing that in falſe, nor willinglie kéepe any thing bac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e that is true. In the Quéenes Bench, there were two detained for Poperie: The one called <hi>Richard Hobſon,</hi> borne in the <hi>Ile</hi> of <hi>Wight,</hi> of good Parentage, young in yéeres (but as tyme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffereth) many young &amp; gréene heades, are ſeaſoned Papiſts. The other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>William Sherwood,</hi> a Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, born<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſome Landes, in <hi>Yorkſhyre,</hi> at <hi>Walking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> by <hi>Byuerley,</hi> a man condempned in a Primanerie, for extolling the Supremacie:
<pb facs="tcp:3161:3"/>a derider of Gods Miniſters, a diſturber of Preachers, a contemner of the ſeruice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by her Maieſtie, calling it diueliſh: one well liked of many Papiſtes, but beſt liked of himſelfe, becauſe he was ſo diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, they accounted him ſtoute: becauſe he prated much, they accounted him learned: but becauſe he hath ſhamed them much, they would now accoumpt him madde. It fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before the death of <hi>Hobſon,</hi> about ſixe wéekes, that <hi>Sherwood</hi> for want of paiment was remooued from his lodging, well ſhake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, to the common Gaile, whoſe miſery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pitied by this young man, was alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeued by his meanes, (as at ſundrie other times he was). The quarrell as I am cred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly enformed was this: <hi>Hobſon</hi> gaue his woord for the money that <hi>Sherwood</hi> owed: a fréend of <hi>Sherwoods</hi> ſhortly after, had ſent fiue pounds for the paiment of his charges, which <hi>Hobſon</hi> receiuing, diſburſed it for himſelfe, and within few daies after, ſatiſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the reſidue, becauſe this money was not paide to <hi>Sherwood</hi> firſt: at Dinner time with open woords he proteſted, that he could not abide <hi>Hobſon.</hi> This young man mooued him oftentimes earneſtly to be reconciled, ſhewing his gréefe vnto him, in that he
<pb facs="tcp:3161:3"/>tooke offence at him, but nothing might moue his minde that thirſted, or ſtaye his hands that itched to commit murther. It is a ſpéeche commonly vſed, that looue waxeth and waneth oftentimes with the Moone, but it may be as commonly ſéene, that the hatred of a Papiſt neuer waxeth and waneth, but ſtill waxeth, ſtill increaſeth: he that hath béene planted in Poperie, his Grapes are Grapes of Gall: his cluſters are alwayes bitter. If the Pope hath once giuen them a Soppe, they are lightly neuer ſober after: if he haue once powred his licker into them, theyr Veſſels can hardely be made cleane. But to be briefe, the day grew on, which was the <hi>28.</hi> of <hi>Iune,</hi> about <hi>8.</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clock in the morning, at which time he had determined, to murder his fellow Papiſt, and that the matter might more eaſy be brought to paſſe, he cauſed the night before the Kéeper to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ue all <hi>Hobſons</hi> weapons, ſo that the next morning, as <hi>Hobſon</hi> was comming downe thorough <hi>Sherwoods</hi> Chamber, from his prayers, <hi>Sherwood</hi> ſhutting his Chamber <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oore, affailed him with a knife, and a ſtoole treſſell, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ouiſhing him, afterwardes gaue him a large wound, kéeping him downe and ſtrugling till he bled to death, <hi>Hobſon</hi> often
<pb facs="tcp:3161:4"/>crying, helpe Father <hi>Throckmorton,</hi> he kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth me with his knife: maiſter <hi>Throckmor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> and others, hearing this noyſe, came vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon <hi>Sherwood,</hi> and by force broke vp his doores, found the young man all to be ſowſed in his own blood, and gaſping for breath: who after a fewe faint words, yéelded his ſoule in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the handes of God. <hi>Sherwood</hi> perceyued a great many buſie about <hi>Hobſon,</hi> began to practiſe to eſcape, but by héede taking of one Maiſter <hi>Smithes</hi> man, he was brought to the <hi>Marshalles</hi> handes, and embrued in his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes blood: who béeing examined, he denied the manifeſt murder, which by witneſſe was prooued, and he béeing brought to the flaine bodie, the blood which was ſettled, iſſued out a treſhe. Thus he ſtewe this young man, in déede and cauſe, miſerably in forme &amp; faſhion, cruelly and beaſtly.</p>
            <p>Let vs aduiſedly now weigh and cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>der, what manner of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>for this is, that cutteth ſo ſharpe: If they be thus vnable to maiſter theyr paſſions, and thus like blood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uckers, do open them againſt theyr owne feliowe priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, what ſhall we looke for at theyr hande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Quibus ſepibus tam immanes bell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus:</hi> What hedges can be made ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to kéepe in theſe beaſtes. <hi>Tullie,</hi> wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:3161:4"/>againſt <hi>Anthonie. Phillip. 7.</hi> ſayth thus: <hi>Qui fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilierem iug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>laret, quid hic occaſions d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta faci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imice? Et qui illud animi cauſa, fee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit hunc prede cauſa quid facturum putetis? <hi>He that wyll kyll his familliar freende, what wyll he doo, if occaſion be offered, to his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie: And he that will doo this of ſtomach, what will he offer to doo for ſpoyle?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely, ſo they will doo as they haue done: they will deuowre poore Proteſtauntes, as Beaſtes eate graſſe, kéeping them vnder: we ſhall (if time ſerued) not onely be choaked with the ſmoake of Poperie, but we ſhall be burnt vp with the fire.</p>
            <p>Their impriſonmentes, haue ſo enritched them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that they abound in all manner of wealth, eſpeciallies no men better furniſhed for warre, for rebellion, then they. In this great tyme of mercie, they doo nothing but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ther heapes of ſtones to throwe at vs. They are making of the halters, to hang vs: they are whetting of their kniues, to cutte our throates. Theſe tye Dogges, when they ſhall be let looſe, they will byte vs, nay, they will hayts vs to death.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3161:5"/>
            <p>It is time to cut of the <hi>Hydra</hi> his heads, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to ſtrangle him within his Caue, for how ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it commeth to paſſe they lift vp their heads on highe, Papiſtry began to wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dead and to be colde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth: it beginneth now to wax warme againe and to neeſe, we poo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Proteſtants are afraide, but that God &amp; our gracious Prince is with vs and hath broke ſtill the arme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked, our harts would mell like wax in the middeſt of our bowels: the Lord hath deliue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d her Maieſtie, hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as Dowe from the hand of the Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>r, and as a Birde from the hand of the Fowler, and God gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nt they be neuer ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for good ſubiects, till they become Iub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to God and his Goſpell. This ſubiection of theirs and falſe Proteſtation of faith to her Maieſtie is a falſe colour, we win<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> hard or elſe we be merue louſly blinded if we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceans it not, God remooue ſuch Subiects from ſo good a Prince. It is piety that theſe black Hauens ſhould go for Birds with the reſt: I hope God will ſo bleſſe vs, eſpecially all Magiſtrates, that they will looke to it at the laſt that they ſhall not be in acco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e with them as to be the finger next the thombe.</p>
            <p>But now to returne to his ende, <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis
<pb facs="tcp:3161:5"/>Vita, finis ita,</hi> as he liued ſo he dyed.</p>
            <p>Beeing araigned at <hi>Croydon,</hi> he continued ſtill obſtinately denying the fact, hoping for ſome healpe by pardon, but a iuſt iudge preuented an vngratious hope.</p>
            <p>The <hi>12.</hi> of <hi>Iuly</hi> he was retourned home manacled with an other, who was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for a rape: his behauiour the night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſuffered, was according to his accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed vſage, reſolute in opinion, though falſe and diſſolute in behauiour, driuing of his Chriſtian brethren that exhorted him, with dry ſcoffes, and no maruell, for ſcoffing mocking and moweing, licking of Chalices and all manner of toying, is the life of their religion.</p>
            <p>The next day was the <hi>13.</hi> of <hi>Iuly,</hi> the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time, for the execution: In the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning certaine deuout Chriſtians had acceſſe vnto him, whom at the firſt entraunce he cut of, or hearing a ſmall time, deſpiſed. The time of the execution drue nighe, which was perfourmed, ouer againſt the Quéenes Benche, where the murder was committed by the vnder Shriefe of <hi>Surrie,</hi> and the Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Southwarke,</hi> from the white Lion, to the place where he ſhould ſuffer, after many
<pb facs="tcp:3161:6"/>vaine words of conceaued repriue had by the way, he was cauſed to clime the Ladder, on which being placed, he entered this kinde of diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>I beſéeche all Romiſh Catholicks to helpe me in this my extremitie, with their vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and godly prayers, for other which are of a contrary profeſſion, as I abhorre their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſo I will none of theyr prayers. But if there ſhalbe here preſent any one of the true Catholick Romiſh faithe: I béeſeth them of theyr prayers in my behalfe.</p>
            <p>The people hearing theſe his obſtinate ſpéeches, with ſundry exclamations, cryed out, hang him, hang him, there be none heere of his profeſſion.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe hee continued his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſpéeches, proclayming the Pope of Rome the ſupreme head of the Univerſall Church, Chriſtes Uicar here vpon earth. Yet notwithſtanding, though by euident reaſons he was confuted, yet the God of this world had ſo blinded him, that no reaſon could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile with him.</p>
            <p>And farther, whereas the Preacher per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded him to lay his hope on Chriſte whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:3161:6"/>mercy was infinite, he vehemently cryed out, away with the Woolfe, he peruerteth the truthe, and troubleth me, away with the Woolfe.</p>
            <p>Béeing farther inquired of the murther, he perſiſted in his vniuſt denyall, laying con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all euidence and probability, the death of the young man <hi>Hobſon</hi> to his owne charge.</p>
            <p>When no hope of confeſſion or recantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was to be conceiued, the Shriefe cauſed him to be remooued higher, to the ende that execution might be perfourmed, wiſhing him by earneſt and deuoute prayers, to call for mercy and repentaunce, to craue grace.</p>
            <p>But he by theſe tokens perceiuing death at hand, contrarie to a méeke Lambe, as he termed him ſelfe, fled downe the Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to flye from the Butcher, thereby ſhowing the vnſtableneſſe of his faythe, ſo that the hangman was enforced to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doo the Halter which he had faſtened to the Iibbet, and to put it about his neck belowe, and ſo by little and little to draw him up.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3161:7"/>
            <p>Where reſting, after many perſwaſions by the Shriefe and the Preacher, and no profit in the middeſt of his Lattine <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> was turned off to the mercy of God.</p>
            <p>I am perſwaded if all the reſt were thus handled, no one faithfull ſubiect ſhould draw leſſe breath, and then I am ſure (thorough Gods great goodnes) the happy peace of this land ſhould be made perfit, you ſée how bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he imbraced forraine iuriſdiction, all they which be Papiſts, hartely doo the like, I pray God that if they be not haltered, yet that they may be bridled with ſhorter Raines, that they be not ſo headſtrong, as this man was.</p>
            <p>If a Shéepe werier be well cougeled at the ſyrſte, he forfaketh his trade: ſo if Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes were thoroughly dealt withall, they would forget to make the Pope ſupreame head of the Church of England.</p>
            <p>I be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>éeche thoſe that be in authoritie to looke to it, and thus committing the poore (yet quiet) eſtate of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, to the olde and wonted care of our grations Prince, and the reſt that beare any office, I end, not willing to ſpend many words vpon ſo vile and carrenly a generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but as <hi>Peter, <hi>Act. 2.</hi>
               </hi> exhorted his ſchollers
<pb facs="tcp:3161:7"/>in many woordes, ſaying, <hi>Saue your ſelues from this froward generation,</hi> ſo I with few words, exhort all eſtates to looke to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and to take héede of this vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and peſtilent generation from auncient cruelty, of the which the Lord deliuer this whole lande of Englande bothe now and for euer. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by <hi>John Charlewood and</hi> Edward VVhite. 1581.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3161:8"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
